GORDON:
I knew Harvey Dent.
I was his friend.
And it will be a very long time before
someone inspires us the way he did.
I believed in Harvey Dent.
Dr. Pavel, I'm CIA.
DRIVER:
He wasn't alone.
- Uh, you don't get to bring friends.
- They are not my friends.
DRIVER:
Don't worry, no charge for them.
CIA OP: And why would I want them? DRIVER:
They were trying to grab your prize.
They work for the mercenary.
The masked man.
- Bane?
- Aye.
Get them on board. I'll call it in.
CIA OP: The flight plan I just filed
with the agency...
...lists me, my men, Dr. Pavel here...
...but only one of you!
First one to talk gets
to stay on my aircraft!
Who paid you to grab Dr. Pavel?
(GUNSHOT)
He didn't fly so good!
Who wants to try next?
Tell me about Bane!
Why does he wear the mask?
A lot of loyalty for a hired gun!
MAN: Well, perhaps he's wondering
why someone would shoot a man...
...before throwing him out of a plane.
At least you can talk.
Who are you?
MAN:
It doesn't matter who we are.
What matters is our plan.
No one cared who I was
till I put on the mask.
If I pull that off, will you die?
BANE:
It would be extremely painful.
You're a big guy.
BANE:
For you.
Was getting caught part of your plan?
BANE:
Of course.
Dr. Pavel refused our
offer in favor of yours.
- We had to find out what he told you...
- Nothing. I said nothing.
Well, congratulations,
you got yourself caught!
- Sir?
- Now what's the next step of your master plan?
BANE:
Crashing this plane...
...with no survivors.
(GUNFIRE)
PILOT:
Mayday, Mayday!
(YELLS)
(GRUNTING)
Aah! What you doing to me? Let me out!
No!
No, no, no! No!
(PAVEL YELLING)
BANE: No! They expect one of us
in the wreckage, brother.
Have we started the fire?
BANE:
Yes, the fire rises.
(PAVEL YELLING)
Calm down, doctor.
Now is not the time for fear.
That comes later.
MAYOR: Harvey Dent Day
may not be our oldest public holiday...
...but we're here tonight
because it's one of the most important.
Harvey Dent's uncompromising stand
against organized crime...
...had made Gotham a safer place than it was
at the time of his death, eight years ago.
This city has seen a historic turnaround.
No city is without crime, but this city is
without organized crime because the Dent Act...
...gave law enforcement teeth
in its fight against the mob.
Now people are talking about
repealing the Dent Act...
...and to them I say, "Not on my watch. "
(AUDIENCE APPLAUDS)
I want to thank the Wayne Foundation
for hosting this event.
I'm told Mr. Wayne couldn't be here tonight.
I'm sure he's with us in spirit.
And now I'm gonna give way
to an important voice...
CONGRESSMAN: You ever lay eyes on Wayne
at one of these things?
No one has. Not in years.
MAYOR:... people put their faith
in a murderous thug in a mask and a cape.
A thug who showed his true nature...
...when he betrayed the trust
of this great man...
...and murdered him in cold blood.
Sweetheart, not so fast with the chow.
- Shrimp balls?
- Thank you.
Jim Gordon can tell you the truth about
Harvey Dent. I'll let him tell you himself.
Commissioner Gordon.
GORDON:
The truth?
I have...
...written a speech...
...telling the truth about Harvey Dent.
Maybe the time isn't right.
Maybe right now...
...all you need to know
is that there are...
...1000 inmates in Blackgate Prison
as a direct result of the Dent Act.
These are violent criminals, essential cogs
in the organized-crime machine.
Maybe, for now, all I should say
about the death of Harvey Dent is this:
It has not been for nothing.
(AUDIENCE APPLAUDS)
MAID 1: You see the guy who owns the house?
MAID 2: No. I heard...
- ... he never leaves the east wing.
- I heard he had an accident.
- Yeah, that he's disfigured. He
has to wear a... ALFRED: Mr. Till?
Why are your people
using the main staircase?
And where's Mrs. Bolton?
SELINA:
Uh, she's at the bar, sir. Can I help?
The east drawing room.
Unlock the door, put the tray on the table,
lock the door again. Nothing more.
ALFRED: I'm sorry, Miss Tate.
I tried, but he won't see you.
And you mustn't take it personally.
Everyone knows that Wayne's holed up
in there with 8-inch nails...
...peeing into Mason jars.
It's very good of you
to let me on the grounds.
DAGGETT: Why are you wasting your time
trying to talk to a man...
...who threw away your investment
on some save-the-world vanity project?
He can't get your money back. I can.
I could try explaining that
a save-the-world project, vain or not...
...is worth investing in, Mr. Daggett.
But you understand only money
and the power you think it buys...
...so why waste my time indeed?
GORDON:
Second shift reports in?
You should spend more time
with the mayor.
Well, that's your department.
CONGRESSMAN:
Anyone shown him the crime stats?
He goes by his gut and it bothers him,
no matter what the numbers.
- Must be popular with his wife.
- Not really. She took the kids to Cleveland.
He'll have plenty of time for visits.
The mayor's gonna dump him in the spring.
- Really?
- Mm-hm.
- But he's a hero.
- A war hero. This is peacetime.
(SHRIEKS)
Oh, sorry, sorry.
I'm so terribly sorry, Mr. Wayne.
It is Mr. Wayne, isn't it?
Although you don't have the long nails
or, heh, the facial scars, sir.
Is that what they say about me?
It's just that no one ever sees you.
That's a beautiful necklace. Reminds me
of one that belonged to my mother.
It can't be the same one...
...because her pearls are in this safe...
...the manufacturer clearly explained...
...is uncrackable.
Oops.
Nobody told me it was uncrackable.
I'm afraid I can't let you take those.
Look, you wouldn't beat up a woman
any more than I would beat up a cripple.
Of course, sometimes
exceptions have to be made.
Good night, Mr. Wayne.
Can I have a ride?
You read my mind.
Let's go.
ALFRED:
Miss Tate was asking to see you again.
WAYNE:
She's very persistent.
And quite lovely,
in case you were wondering.
- I wasn't.
- What are you doing?
Examining print dust.
We've been robbed.
And this is your idea
of, uh, sounding the alarm, is it?
She took the pearls,
tracking device and all.
- She?
- One of the maids.
Perhaps you should stop letting them
in this side of the house.
Perhaps you should start learning
to make your own bed.
- Why were you dusting for prints?
- I wasn't.
She was.
Sir. Congressman Gilly's wife
has been calling in.
The congressman never made it home
after the Wayne Foundation event.
That's a job for the police?
When you and Dent cleaned the streets,
you cleaned them good.
Pretty soon we'll be chasing down, uh,
overdue library books.
(GORDON CHUCKLES)
And yet here you are,
like we're still at war.
- What's your name, son?
- Blake, sir.
You have something you want to ask me?
It's about that night. This night,
eight years ago. The night Dent died.
The last confirmed sighting of the Batman.
He murders those people,
takes down two SWAT teams...
...breaks Dent's neck
and then just vanishes?
I'm not hearing a question, son.
Don't you want to know who he was?
I know exactly who he was.
He was the Batman.
(GORDON SIGHS)
Let's go see about the congressman's wife.
ALFRED:
Master Wayne?
You haven't been down here in a long time.
Trying to find out more about
our jewel thief. I ran her prints.
Unless she's lost a lot of weight...
...she was wearing
someone else's fingerprints.
She's good.
She may be, but we have a trace
on the necklace.
We do. I cross-referenced the address
she went back to...
...with police data
on high-end B-and-E's, and, um...
Selina Kyle.
The databases are full of close-calls,
tips from fences.
She's good, but the ground
is shrinking beneath her feet.
We should send the police
before she fences the pearls.
She won't. She likes them too much.
And they weren't what she was after.
- What was she after?
- My fingerprints.
It was printer toner
mixed with graphite on the safe.
It gives a good pull and it's untraceable.
Fascinating. You two should
exchange notes over coffee.
You're trying to set me
up with a jewel thief?
At this point, I'd set you up with a chimpanzee,
if it brought you back to the world.
There's nothing out there for me.
And that's the problem.
You hung up your cape and your cowl
but you didn't move on.
You never went to find a life.
To find someone.
Alfred...
...I did find someone.
I know, and you lost them.
But that's all part of living, sir.
But you're not living, you're just waiting,
hoping for things to go bad again.
Remember when you left Gotham?
Before all this, before Batman?
You were gone seven year.
Seven years I waited,
hoping that you wouldn't come back.
Every year, I took a holiday.
I went to Florence.
There's this café
on the banks of the Arno.
Every fine evening I'd sit there
and order a Fernet Branca.
I had this fantasy...
...that I would look across the tables...
...and I'd see you there, with a wife.
Maybe a couple of kids.
You wouldn't say anything to me,
nor me to you.
But we'd both know that you'd made it.
That you were happy.
I never wanted you to come back to Gotham.
I always knew there was nothing here
for you, except pain and tragedy.
And I wanted something
more for you than that.
I still do.
DWP MAN: They wash up here
a couple of times a month.
More when it gets colder.
Homeless, sheltering in the tunnels.
We pulled him from the basin,
but other than that we didn't touch him.
ROSS: What?
BLAKE: Name's Jimmy.
He's from St. Swithin's.
It's the boys' home
where I coach some ball.
REILLY:
Jimmy hadn't been around for months.
BLAKE: No? Why?
- Blake, you know why.
He aged out. We don't have the resources
to keep boys on after 16.
I thought the Wayne Foundation
gave money for that.
Not for the past couple of years.
- He has a brother here, doesn't he?
- Mark. I'll tell him.
I'd like to, if that's all right.
You know what he was doing
in the tunnels?
Lot of guys been going down the tunnels
when they age out.
Say you can live down there.
Say there's work down there.
Work?
What kind of work are you
gonna find in the sewers?
More than you can find up here, I guess.
BLAKE:
So you know about him?
Of course.
Do you think he's coming back?
I don't know.
STRYVER:
You brought a date?
I like having someone around
to open doors for me.
Right hand. No partials.
- Very nice.
- Mm-hm.
Not so fast, handsome.
You got something for me?
Ah, yes.
(SIGHS)
I don't know what you're planning to do
with Mr. Wayne's prints...
...but I'm guessing you'll need his thumb.
You don't count so good, huh?
I count fine.
In fact, I'm counting to 10 right now.
Okay.
My friend's outside. Just hit "send. "
(KNOCK ON DOOR)
This place is a little dead.
It'll liven up in a minute. Trust me.
Is everything okay?
Great. Catch you later.
(DOOR OPENS THEN CLOSES)
Hmm.
It would have been a lot easier...
...to just give me what we agreed.
We can't have loose ends.
And even in that dress,
no one's gonna miss you.
SELINA:
No.
But my friend over there?
Every cop in the city's missing him.
STRYVER:
That's cute.
But they're not gonna be looking
in a place like this.
I don't know.
You did just use his cell phone.
(TIRES SCREECHING NEARBY)
SWAT 1: Go!
SWAT 2: Go!
SWAT 3:
Police! Get down now!
(SCREAMING)
SELINA:
Help me! Help me!
Help me, please! Please help me!
(SOBS)
(GUNFIRE OUTSIDE)
Keep some pressure on that, sweetheart.
Call me?
BLAKE: You okay, miss?
- He's bleeding. You gotta help him.
I got the congressman.
(SIRENS WAIL)
SWAT 4:
Clear!
GORDON: Manhole! Get this up!
Get the DWP down here!
You three, down with me.
You two, you go down,
cover the next exit!
What, they went down there?
(GORDON GRUNTS)
- We're gonna go down there, right?
FOLEY: That was a gas explosion, kid.
- Wasn't gas. It's a sewer.
- No one goes in till we know what's there.
We know, sir. The police commissioner.
Someone get this hothead out of here?
And where's that DWP guy?
BANE:
Why are you here?
(GORDON GRUNTS)
Answer him.
BANE:
I was asking you.
It's the police commissioner.
BANE:
And you brought him down here?
MERCENARY 1: We didn't know what to do.
BANE: You panicked.
And your weakness has cost the lives
of three others.
No, he's alone.
(NECK SNAPS)
BANE:
Search him.
Then I will kill you.
(MERCENARIES SHOUTING)
- He's dead.
BANE: So show me his body.
The water runs to any one of the outflows.
We'd never find him.
BANE: Follow him!
MERCENARY 2: Follow him?
(GUNSHOT)
You okay? You okay?
Hey, hey, you awake?
(GORDON COUGHING)
(KNOCK ON DOOR)
I need to see Bruce Wayne.
I'm sorry, Mr. Wayne doesn't take
unscheduled calls.
Even from a police officer.
And if I go get a warrant for
the investigation of Harvey Dent's murder?
That still count as unscheduled?
WAYNE:
What can I do for you, officer?
BLAKE:
Commissioner Gordon's been shot.
He chased a gunman
down into the sewers.
When I pulled him out, he was babbling
about an underground army.
A masked man called Bane.
Shouldn't you be telling
your superior officers?
They asked me if he saw
any giant alligators.
He needs you.
He needs the Batman.
- If Commissioner Gordon thinks...
- Oh, he doesn't know or care who you are.
But we've met before.
It was a long time ago. I was a kid.
Uh, St. Swithin's.
It used to be funded by
the Wayne Foundation. It's an orphanage.
My mom died when I was small. It was
a car accident, I don't really remember it.
But my dad got shot a couple years later
over a gambling debt...
...and I remember that one just fine.
Not a lot of people know
what it feels like, do they?
To be angry...
...in your bones.
I mean, they understand.
Foster parents.
Everybody understands...
...for a while.
And then they want the angry little kid
to do something he knows he can't do.
Move on.
So after a while,
they stop understanding.
They send the angry kid to a boys' home.
I figured it out too late.
You gotta learn to hide the anger.
Practice smiling in a mirror.
It's like putting on a mask.
So you showed up this one day,
in a cool car.
Pretty girl on your arm.
We were so excited.
Bruce Wayne, billionaire orphan.
I mean, we used to make up stories
about you, man. Legends.
And, you know, with the other kids,
that's all it was, just stories, but...
Right when I saw you,
I knew who you really were.
I'd seen that look on your face before.
It's the same one I taught myself.
I don't know why you took the fall
for Dent's murder...
...but I'm still a
believer in the Batman...
...even if you're not.
Why did you say that your boys' home used
to be funded by the Wayne Foundation?
BLAKE:
Because the money stopped.
Might be time to get some fresh air.
Start paying attention to the details.
Some of those details
might need your help.
WAYNE:
You check that name? Bane?
ALFRED: He's a mercenary.
No other known names.
Him and his men were behind
a coup in West Africa...
...that secured mining operations
for our friend John Daggett.
WAYNE: Now Daggett's brought them here.
- Or so it seems.
- I'll keep digging.
- Yeah.
Alfred, why did the Wayne Foundation
stop funding boys' homes in the city?
The foundation is funded by
the profits of Wayne Enterprises.
There have to be some.
- Time to talk to Mr. Fox, I think.
- I'll get him on the phone.
No, no, no. Do we still have
any cars around the place?
Yes. One or two.
I need an appointment at the hospital
for my leg.
- Which hospital?
- Whichever one Jim Gordon's in.
DOCTOR: I have seen worse cartilage in knees.
WAYNE: That's good.
No. That's because there is
no cartilage in your knee.
And not much of any use
in your elbows or your shoulders.
Between that and the scar tissue
on your kidneys...
...the residual concussive damage
to your brain tissue...
...and the general scarred-over quality
of your body...
...I cannot recommend that you go heli-skiing.
- Right.
We were in this together...
...then you were gone.
WAYNE:
The Batman wasn't needed any more.
- We won.
- Based on a lie.
And now there's evil rising
from where we tried to bury it.
The Batman has to come back.
What if he doesn't exist any more?
He must.
YUPPIE:
You took my goddamn wallet, didn't you?
- You f... You took my wallet!
- No, I...
- Get out.
YUPPIE: She took my... Ah!
- Now.
YUPPIE: Creep!
I don't know what he's so upset about.
There's only 60 bucks in here.
Probably the watch.
(CHUCKLES)
(CHATTERING)
MAN 1:
Who's that?
MAN 2: A stiff can barely
climb out of his sports car.
- No, that's Bruce Wayne!
- Mr. Wayne, over here!
(ALL SHOUTING)
(BUTTON BEEPS & DEVICES POWER OFF)
WAYNE: I'm not sure if my assistant...
- Right through here.
Thank you so much.
(CLASSICAL MUSIC PLAYING)
MIRANDA:
Bruce Wayne at a charity ball.
Miss Tate, isn't it?
Even before you became a recluse,
you never came to these things.
The proceeds go to the big fat spread.
It's not about charity.
It's about feeding the ego
of whichever society hag laid this on.
Actually, this is my party, Mr. Wayne.
Oh.
And the proceeds will go where they should,
because I paid for the big fat spread myself.
That's very generous of you.
You have to invest if you want to restore
balance to the world.
Take our clean-energy project.
Sometimes the investment
doesn't pay off.
- I'm sorry.
- You have a practiced apathy, Mr. Wayne.
But a man who doesn't care about the world
doesn't spend half his fortune to save it.
And isn't so wounded when it fails...
...that he goes into hiding.
Have a good evening, Mr. Wayne.
WAYNE:
Mind if I cut in?
Thank you.
(WAYNE CHUCKLES)
- You don't seem happy to see me.
- You were supposed to be a shut-in.
I felt like some fresh air.
Why didn't you call the police?
I have a powerful friend
who deals with things like this.
That's a brazen costume for a cat burglar.
Yeah? Who are you pretending to be?
Bruce Wayne, eccentric billionaire.
- Who's your date?
SELINA: His wife's in Ibiza.
She left her diamonds behind, though.
Worried they might get stolen.
It's pronounced "Ibiza. "
You wouldn't want these folks realizing
you're a crook, not a social climber.
You think I care what anyone
in this room thinks of me?
I doubt you care what anyone
in any room thinks of you.
Don't condescend, Mr. Wayne.
You don't know a thing about me.
Well, Selina Kyle, I know you came here
from your walk-up in Old Town.
A modest place for a master jewel thief.
Which means that either
you're saving for retirement...
...or you're in deep with the wrong people.
You don't get to judge me because you were
born in the master bedroom of Wayne Manor.
- Actually, I was born in the Regency Room.
- I started out doing what I had to.
Once you've done what you had to,
they never let you do what you want to.
Start fresh.
Ugh. There's no fresh
start in today's world.
Any 12-year-old with a cell phone
could find out what you did.
Everything we do is collated
and quantified. Everything sticks.
Is that how you justify stealing?
I take what I need from those
who have more than enough.
I don't stand on the shoulders
of people with less.
Robin Hood?
I think I'd do more to help someone than
most of the people in this room. Than you.
You think maybe you're assuming
a little too much?
Maybe you're being unrealistic about what's
really in your pants other than your wallet.
Ouch.
You think all this can last?
There's a storm coming, Mr. Wayne.
You and your friends better batten down
the hatches, because when it hits...
...you're all gonna wonder how you
ever thought you could live so large...
...and leave so little for the rest of us.
You sound like
you're looking forward to it.
I'm adaptable.
Those pearls do look better on you
than they did in my safe.
But I still can't let you keep them.
MAN:
You... You scared her off!
Not likely.
Must have lost my ticket.
- Your wife said you were taking a cab home.
- My wife?
Just you, sir?
Don't worry, Master Wayne.
Takes a little time to get back
in the swing of things.
Bruce Wayne, as I live and breathe.
What brings you out of cryo-sleep,
Mr. Wayne?
You haven't lost your sense of humor.
Even if you have lost most of my money.
Actually, you did that.
If you funnel your entire R and D budget...
...into a fusion project
that you then mothball...
...your company is unlikely to thrive.
What are my options?
Well, if you're unwilling
to turn on the machine...
I can't. I can't, Lucius.
Well, then sit tight.
Your majority keeps Daggett at bay...
...while we figure out a future for
the energy program with Miranda Tate.
She has supported the project
all the way.
She's smart. And quite lovely.
We all just want what's
best for you, Bruce.
Show her the machine.
I'll think it over.
Anything else?
Nope. Why?
These conversations used to end
with an unusual request.
I retired.
Mm-hm. Well, let me show you
some stuff anyway.
Just for old times' sake.
WAYNE: I figured you'd have
shut this place down.
FOX:
Oh, it was always shut down, officially.
WAYNE:
All this new stuff.
FOX: After your father died, Wayne Enterprises
set up 14 different defense subsidiaries.
For years, I've been shuttering
and consolidating...
...all the different prototypes
under one roof.
- My roof.
- Why?
Keep them from falling
into the wrong hands.
Oh, now you're just showing off.
Defense Department projects
for tight geometry urban pacification.
Rotors are configured to maneuver
between buildings without recirculation.
What's it called?
Oh, it has a long, uninteresting
Wayne Enterprises designation.
I just took to calling it the Bat.
And, yes, Mr. Wayne, it does come in black.
Works fine, except for the autopilot.
Takes a better mind than mine to fix it.
Better mind?
Well, I was trying to be modest.
A less busy mind.
Yours.
(CRACKING)
(WAYNE GROANING)
ALFRED: Is it really painful?
- You're very welcome to try it, Alfred.
Happy watching. Thank you, sir.
Not bad.
Not bad at all.
If you're seriously considering
going back out there...
...you should hear the rumors
surrounding Bane.
WAYNE:
I'm all ears.
There is a prison
in a more ancient part of the world.
A pit where men are thrown
to suffer and die.
But sometimes
a man rises from the darkness.
Sometimes the pit sends something back.
WAYNE: Bane.
- Bane.
Born and raised in hell on earth.
- Born in a prison?
- No one knows why, or how he escaped.
But they do know that once he did...
...he was trained by Ra's Al Ghul,
your mentor.
Bane was a member
of the League of Shadows?
And then he was excommunicated.
And any man who is too extreme
for Ra's Al Ghul is not to be trifled with.
I didn't realize I was known
for trifling with criminals.
That was then.
And you can strap up your leg
and put your mask back on...
...but that doesn't make you
what you were.
If this man is everything that you
say he is, then the city needs me.
The city needs Bruce Wayne.
Your resources. Your knowledge.
It doesn't need your body, or your life.
That time's past.
You're afraid that if I go back out there,
I'll fail.
No.
I'm afraid that you want to.
(BELL RINGS)
(CLAMORING)
TRADER: You can't short the stock because
Bruce Wayne goes to a party.
Wayne coming back is change.
Change is either good or bad. I vote bad.
On what basis?
I flipped a coin.
It says rye... I said no rye, man.
Hey, rookie, lose the helmet.
We need faces for camera.
(DEVICE BEEPING)
(TRADER CHUCKLES)
Come on. Let's go scalping.
Come on.
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
MERCENARY 1:
Everybody down, now!
This is a stock exchange.
There's no money you can steal.
BANE:
Really? Then why are you people here?
SECURITY CHIEF: Everybody, stay back!
Go down to the end of the block!
We have an emergency situation!
You gotta get in there!
This is a hostage situation.
No, this is a robbery. They have
direct access to the online trading desk.
I'm not risking my men for your money.
We have to ask you to move.
We have a situation.
It's not our money, it's everybody's.
Really? Mine's in my mattress.
You don't put these guys down, that stuffing in
your mattress might be worth a whole lot less.
Cut the fiber cable
and take out that cell tower.
SECURITY CHIEF: Thank you.
FOLEY: That'll slow them down.
COP:
Move back!
All the way! Go! Sir, get back, please!
They cut the fiber.
Cell's working.
BANE:
For now.
Get all these barriers up. All of them up. No
one gets in or out of any of these streets.
Where am I supposed to move it?
Back it up.
All right, just stay in your vehicle, okay?
BANE: How much longer
does the program need?
Eight minutes.
BANE:
Time to go mobile.
MERCENARY 1:
Everybody, up!
(GUNFIRE)
You two, move!
BANE:
Thank you.
FOLEY:
Steady.
SNIPER:
I've got something.
SECURITY CHIEF:
Hold your fire, they've got hostages.
Hold your fire!
(SHRIEKS)
(HOSTAGE 1 YELLING)
Go, go!
HOSTAGE 1:
Please! Just let me go!
Hey, please! Hey!
Shoot the tires.
There's no shot.
Now back off.
Back off, they've got hostages.
MAN (ON TV):... P.D. are pursuing
the four suspects through downtown...
...in response to a hostage situation.
What's going on with the lights?
(ELECTRICAL SYSTEMS POWER DOWN)
VETERAN COP:
It can't be.
What the hell was that?
Oh, boy, you are in
for a show tonight, son.
HOSTAGE 2:
Please! Help, help, help!
(POWERS UP)
(GUNSHOT)
Sorry.
Put that thing away
before you hurt yourself. Get in!
Let's go. You, get in the car.
They've spotted the Batman.
Call everyone in.
Every car patrol, beat cop, off-duty too.
Pull them in now. I'm gonna do
what Jim Gordon never could.
- What's that?
- I'm gonna take down the Batman.
MAN 1 (OVER TV):... are confirming
four suspects are carrying two hostages...
...kidnapped from
the Gotham Stock Exchange.
- Reports from the eyewitnesses...
MAN 2: Scott, dead center of your screen.
MAN 1: What do you see?
MAN 2: I see Batman.
MAN 1: Hard to believe, but the suspects
are now being pursued...
...by what appears to be the Batman.
Well, what do you know?
Sir, what about the armed robbers?
HOSTAGE 1:
Please! Just let me go! Please!
SPOTTER (OVER RADIO): One bike's pulled off.
No hostage. Should we pursue?
Negative. Stay on the Batman.
- He's getting away.
- Who do you wanna catch?
Some robber, or the son of a bitch
who killed Harvey Dent?
MAN 1 (OVER TV):
... The entire upper west hill...
Central Heights
and East Park Side areas.
DAGGETT:
Eight years, and he has to pick tonight.
He's drawing the cops off Bane.
HOSTAGE 1:
Please! Just let me go!
Please!
(MAN 1 SCREAMS)
(GROANS)
(SIRENS WAILING NEARBY)
COP (OVER RADIO):
We lost him.
How could you lose him?
COP:
He's got a lot of firepower.
What, and you don't?
COP:
He's heading back downtown.
Then he's as dumb as he dresses.
Close it off, gentlemen.
(BARKING)
Like a rat in a trap, gentlemen.
You might have
the wrong animal there, sir.
You sure it was him?
STRYVER: Bane says the Batman interfered,
but the task was accomplished.
What about the men they arrested?
He said, and I quote,
"They would die before talking. "
Where does he find these guys?
Open the champagne.
And can we get some girls in here?
CATWOMAN:
Careful what you wish for.
Cat got your tongue?
You dumb bitch.
Nobody ever accused me
of being dumb.
You're dumb for coming here tonight.
(DAGGETT GROANS)
I want what you owe me.
(GUN CLICKS)
Want doesn't get.
Nice outfit.
Those heels make it tough to walk?
- I don't know.
- Aah!
Do they?
- So where is it?
- Where's what?
The program. The "clean slate. "
The ultimate tool for a master thief
with a record.
BODYGUARD:
Hold it right there!
(DAGGETT YELLS)
Where is it?
The clean slate?
Where you type in someone's name,
date of birth...
...in a few minutes they're gone
from every database on earth?
- Sound a little too good to be true?
- You're lying!
Rykin Data took it to prototype stage.
That's why I bought them.
But they had nothing.
It was a gangland myth.
CATWOMAN:
Stay back!
I'm not bluffing!
BATMAN:
They know.
They just don't care.
You've gotta be kidding me.
- No guns. No killing.
- Where's the fun in that?
My mother warned me about
getting into cars with strange men.
This isn't a car.
See you around.
You're welcome.
I had it under control.
Those weren't street thugs.
They were trained killers.
I saved your life.
In return, I need to know what you did
with Bruce Wayne's fingerprints.
Wayne wasn't kidding about
a powerful friend.
I sold his prints to Daggett...
...for something that doesn't even exist.
- I doubt many people get the better of you.
- Hey, when a girl's desperate...
- What's he gonna do with them?
- I don't know...
...but Daggett seemed pretty interested
in that mess at the stock market.
(HELICOPTER WHIRRING ABOVE)
Miss Kyle?
So that's what that feels like.
I see from the television coverage that you
got your taste for wanton destruction back.
I retrieved this.
Aren't the police supposed
to be investigating, then?
- They don't have the tools to analyze it.
- They would if you gave them to them.
One man's tool is another man's weapon.
In your mind, perhaps. But there aren't
many things you can't turn into a weapon.
Alfred, enough.
The police weren't getting it done.
Perhaps they might have if you
hadn't made a sideshow of yourself.
- You thought I didn't have it in me.
- You led a bloated police force on a chase...
...with a load of fancy new toys from Fox.
What about when you come up
against him? What then?
- I'll fight harder. I always have.
- Look. His speed, his ferocity, his training.
I see the power of belief.
I see the League of Shadows resurgent.
You said he was excommunicated.
By Ra's Al Ghul.
Who leads them now?
Ra's Al Ghul was the League of Shadows
and I beat him.
Bane is a mercenary.
We need to find out what he's up to.
Trades of some kind. Coded.
And my fingerprint,
courtesy of Selina Kyle.
Get this to Fox.
He can crack the code and tell us
what trades they were executing.
I'll get this to Mr. Fox, but no more.
I've sewn you up, I've set your bones,
but I won't bury you.
I've buried enough members
of the Wayne family.
- You'll leave me?
- You see only one end to your journey.
Leaving is all I have
to make you understand.
You're not Batman any more.
You have to find another way.
You used to talk about finishing,
about a life beyond that awful cave.
Alfred, Rachel died knowing that
we had decided to be together.
That was my life beyond the cave.
I can't just move on.
She... She didn't. She couldn't.
What if she had?
She... I can't change that.
What if before she died
she wrote a letter...
...saying she chose
Harvey Dent over you?
And what if...
...to spare you pain...
...I burnt that letter?
How dare you use Rachel to try to stop me?
I am using the truth, Master Wayne.
Maybe it's time we all stopped trying to
outsmart the truth and let it have its day.
- I'm sorry.
- You're sorry?
You expect to destroy my world...
...and then think that
we're gonna shake hands?
No, no, no.
I know what this means.
What does it mean?
It means your hatred.
And it also means losing someone
that I have cared for...
...since I first heard his cries echo...
...through this house.
But it might also mean saving your life.
And that is more important.
Goodbye, Alfred.
(DOORBELL RINGING)
Alfred?
- Answering your own door?
- Yeah.
Page three.
Seems you made a series of large
put options on the futures exchange...
...verified by thumbprint.
Those options expired
at midnight last night.
Long-term, we may be able to prove fraud.
But for now, you're completely broke...
...and Wayne Enterprises is about to fall
into the hands of John Daggett.
The weapons. We can't let Daggett
get his hands on Applied Sciences.
Applied Sciences is all looked up
and off the books.
The energy project, however,
is a different story.
Miranda Tate.
Let's convince the board to get behind her.
Let's show her the reactor.
We're meeting her there in 35 minutes,
so you better get dressed.
MIRANDA: You brought me out here
to show me this, Mr. Fox?
FOX:
Bear with me, Miss Tate.
Please keep hands and feet inside
the car at all times.
This is it, isn't it?
The reactor is beneath the river...
...so it can be instantly flooded
in the event of a security breach.
Is Bruce Wayne really that paranoid?
FOX:
I'm gonna plead the fifth on that one.
WAYNE: I thought you might like to see
what your investment built.
MIRANDA:
No fossil fuels.
Free clean energy for an entire city.
MIRANDA: Three years ago,
a Russian scientist published a paper...
...on weaponized fusion reactions.
One week later, your reactor
started developing problems.
I think this machine works.
Miranda, if it were operational,
the danger to Gotham would be too great.
Would it make you feel better to know
that the Russian scientist...
...died in a plane crash six months ago?
Someone will work out what Dr. Pavel did.
Someone will figure out a way to make
this power source into a nuclear weapon.
I need you to take control
of Wayne Enterprises...
...and this reactor.
To do what with it?
Nothing.
Until we can guarantee its safety.
And if we can't?
Decommission it. Flood it.
Destroy the world's best chance
for a sustainable future?
If the world's not ready, yes.
Bruce, if you want to save the world,
you have to start trusting it.
I'm trusting you.
Doesn't count. You have no choice.
I could have flooded this chamber
at any time.
I'm choosing to trust you.
Please.
(BOARD MEMBERS CHATTERING)
All right, ladies and gentlemen.
This meeting will now come to order.
DAGGETT: I'd like to point out that we have
a non-board member here...
...which is highly irregular,
even if his family name is above the door.
Bruce Wayne's family built this company.
And he himself has run it.
Into the ground, sir! Does anybody disagree?
Check the share price this morning.
Crazy gambling on futures has not
only cost Mr. Wayne his seat...
...it's cost us all a lot of money.
And he has to go.
I'm afraid he has a point, Mr. Wayne.
Now, back to business.
MAN 1: Mr. Wayne, over here! MAN 2:
How's it feel to be one of the people?
Mr. Wayne, they're towing your car! I
didn't know what to do, they had paperwork.
Looks like you need a ride, huh?
MAN 3:
Wayne, we'll give you a ride!
How the hell did Miranda Tate get
the inside track on the Wayne board?
She been meeting with him?
Sleeping with him?
- Not that we know of.
- You don't know much of anything, do you?
- Where's Bane?
- We told him it was urgent.
- Where is that masked...?
BANE: Speak of the devil...
...and he shall appear.
What the hell is going on?
BANE: The plan is proceeding as expected.
DAGGETT: Oh, really?
Do I look like I'm running
Wayne Enterprises right now?
Your hit on the stock exchange,
it didn't work, my friend.
And now you have my construction crews
going around the city at 24 hours a day.
How exactly is that supposed to help
my company absorb Wayne's?
BANE: Leave us.
- No. You stay here.
I'm in charge.
BANE:
Do you feel in charge?
I've paid you a small fortune.
BANE:
And this gives you power over me?
What is this?
Your money and infrastructure
have been important...
...till now.
What are you?
BANE:
I'm Gotham's reckoning.
Here to end the borrowed time
you've all been living on.
You're pure evil.
BANE:
I'm necessary evil.
DAGGETT:
No. No, no, no!
(DAGGETT SCREAMS)
BLAKE:
When you started, why the mask?
- To protect the people closest to me.
- But you were a loner, right?
- You didn't have any family?
- There are always people you care about.
You just don't realize how much
until they're gone.
The idea was to be a symbol.
Batman could be anybody.
That was the point.
- Well, it was damn good to see him back.
- Not everybody agrees.
- They'll figure that out in the end.
- You got anything on Bane's whereabouts?
Yeah. I got 500 pages of tunnel records
and a flashlight.
I could use some help, actually.
You know what? Drop me in Old Town.
WAYNE:
Hey, hey, hey. I don't think so!
JEN: That's the way this works!
WAYNE: I don't think so!
- That is the way...
SELINA: He's not a mark.
And he doesn't have a cent
to his name, anyway.
Yeah, it's not much.
But it's more than you've got right now.
Actually, they're letting
me keep the house.
The rich don't even go broke
the same as the rest of us, huh?
My powerful friend might hope
to change your mind about leaving.
- And how would he do that?
- By giving you what you want.
- It doesn't exist.
- He says it does.
He wants to meet tonight.
Why?
He needs to find Bane.
Says you'd know how.
- Tell him I'll think about it.
- Okay.
I like your place.
Mr. Wayne?
I'm sorry they took all your money.
No, you're not.
FOLEY: Can we help you, officer?
- Uh, yeah.
John Daggett's body was just found
in a Dumpster about an hour ago.
- Thought you might want to know.
- Why?
His name's all over these permits I just
pulled to, uh, map the tunnels under Gotham.
That's MTA maintenance, uh,
sewer construction, couple of other things.
Where did you get to
with the tunnel searches?
Remind me to tell detail
to keep hotheads out.
We've had teams down there.
It's a huge network.
Well, get more men. Work a grid.
I want him found.
Yeah, the, uh, masked man. We're on it.
Lose the uniform,
you're working for me now.
We could use some hotter heads
around here.
- Sir, that could also be a coincidence.
- You're a detective now, son.
You're not allowed to believe
in coincidence any more.
(THUNDER RUMBLES)
MIRAN DA:
Nobody's answering.
No.
I'm on my own now.
Do you have keys?
Never needed them.
Hope you didn't like me for my money.
MIRANDA:
Suffering builds character.
I'll take care of your
parents' legacy, Bruce.
Who's this?
Where's Alfred?
He left...
...taking everything.
What's that?
My power's been shut off.
(MIRANDA CHUCKLES)
WAYNE:
You're good at that.
When I was a child,
we had almost nothing.
But on the nights when we had a fire,
we felt very rich indeed.
I assumed your family was wealthy.
Not always.
Not when I was young.
An old mistake.
I've made a few myself.
More than a few.
We could leave.
Tonight.
Take my plane, go anywhere we wanted.
Someday, perhaps.
Not tonight.
Don't be shy.
Wayne says you can get me
the clean slate.
- That depends.
- On what?
On what you want it for.
I acquired it to keep it out
of the wrong hands.
Still don't trust me, huh?
How can we change that?
Start by taking me to Bane.
You asked.
From here,
Bane's men patrol the tunnels.
And they're not your average brawlers.
BATMAN:
Neither am I.
- He's behind you.
- Who?
BATMAN:
Me.
MERCENARY 1:
What do you think you're...?
CATWOMAN:
Just a little further.
I had to find a way to stop them
trying to kill me.
You made a serious mistake.
BANE:
Not as serious as yours, I fear.
Bane.
BANE:
Let's not stand on ceremony here...
...Mr. Wayne.
Peace has cost you your strength.
Victory has defeated you.
(BATMAN GRUNTING)
(BATMAN YELLS)
BANE: Theatricality and deception,
powerful agents to the uninitiated.
But we are initiated, aren't we, Bruce?
Members of the League of Shadows.
And you betrayed us.
BATMAN:
"Us"? You were excommunicated...
...by a gang of psychopaths.
BANE:
I am the League of Shadows.
And I'm here to fulfill
Ra's Al Ghul's destiny.
You fight like a younger man.
Nothing held back.
Admirable, but mistaken.
Oh, you think darkness is your ally?
But you merely adopted the dark.
I was born in it.
Molded by it.
I didn't see the light
until I was already a man.
By then, it was nothing to me
but blinding!
The shadows betray you
because they belong to me!
I will show you where
I have made my home...
...whilst preparing to bring justice.
Then I will break you.
Your precious armory.
Gratefully accepted. We will need it.
Ah, yes. I was wondering
what would break first.
(BATMAN YELLS)
Your spirit...
...or your body.
Get me Commissioner Gordon. I got a line
on the congressman's kidnapping.
- Excuse me, miss.
- Uh, yes?
I'm gonna need to see your ticket
and identification, please.
Oh. Do you mind?
I showed your picture to
the congressman. Guess what.
Don't tell me. Still in love?
Oh, head over heels.
Pressing charges, though.
You've made some mistakes, Ms. Kyle.
- Girl's gotta eat.
- And you have an appetite.
Why would you run?
You can't hide with a record like this.
Maybe it's not you I'm running from.
Who then? Bane?
What do you know about him?
That you should be as afraid of him
as I am.
We can offer you protection.
Okay.
When I spotted you, I was looking
for a friend of mine. Bruce Wayne.
Did they kill him?
I'm not sure.
(GASPS)
Why didn't you just...
...kill me?
BANE:
You don't fear death, you welcome it.
Your punishment must be more severe.
Torture?
Yes.
But not of your body.
Of your soul.
Where am I?
BANE:
Home.
Where I learned the truth about despair.
As will you.
There is a reason why this prison
is the worst hell on earth:
Hope.
Every man who has rotted here
over the centuries...
...has looked up to the light
and imagined climbing to freedom.
So easy.
So simple.
And like shipwrecked men turning
to seawater from uncontrollable thirst...
...many have died trying.
I learned here there can be
no true despair without hope.
So as I terrorize Gotham...
...I will feed its people hope
to poison their souls.
I will let them believe
that they can survive...
...so that you can watch them clambering
over each other to stay in the sun.
You can watch me torture an entire city.
And then when you have truly understood
the depth of your failure...
...we will fulfill Ra's Al Ghul's destiny.
We will destroy Gotham.
And then, when it is done...
...and Gotham is...
...ashes...
...then you have my permission to die.
(YELLS)
(GROANS)
(MEN CHEERING AND WHOOPING)
GUARD:
You're looking her up in here?
The Dent Act allows non-segregation
based on extraordinary need.
First time she broke out
of women's correctional, she was 16.
INMATE:
Little closer, baby.
Why, honey? You wanna hold my hand?
(INMATE YELLS)
She's gonna be fine.
FOX: I still don't see the need of a
board meeting for the energy project.
MIRANDA:
Bruce got a lot of things right.
Keeping the board in the dark
was not one of them.
BANE:
How good of you to join us.
Chair. President.
All I need now is one more
ordinary board member.
Mr. Fox, would you like to nominate?
FREDERICKS:
No.
I will volunteer.
FOX:
Where are you taking us?
(DRILLING)
You were right, commissioner.
Will you excuse us, please?
What happened?
Your masked man kidnapped
the Wayne Enterprises board.
He let most of them go,
but he took three into the sewers.
No more patrols. No more hide and seek.
Get every available cop down there
and smoke him out!
The mayor won't want panic.
So it's a training exercise.
I'm sorry I didn't take you seriously.
GORDON:
Not you.
You're telling me the Batman's gone...
...so you chase up the Daggett leads
any way you can.
Yes, sir.
(MAN SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
He asks how much you would pay us
to let you die.
I told him. I told him you have nothing.
Do it for the pleasure.
They pay me more than that
to keep you alive.
(PRISONERS CHANTING)
He will try the climb.
(GROANS)
WAYNE:
Has anyone ever made it?
Of course not.
(YELLS)
(SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
He says there is one who did.
A child.
A child born in this hell.
Bane.
An old legend. Nothing more.
WAYNE:
Don't.
Whatever it is they want you to see,
it's happening soon.
MERCENARY:
Fire in the hole!
(EXPLOSION NEARBY)
BANE:
Turn it on.
I only need one other board member.
There are eight others waiting.
I won't do it.
MIRANDA:
All right, stop.
Lucius, you'll kill this man,
and yourself...
...and you'll barely slow them down.
(MACHINE BEEPS)
(MACHINE POWERS UP)
BANE:
Go on, then. Do your work.
Take them up to the surface.
People of their status...
...deserve to experience
the next era of western civilization.
BLAKE: I've been to half of Daggett's cement
plants and locations they poured underground.
GORDON (OVER PHONE):
Anything strange about the pourings?
Honestly, commissioner, I don't know
anything about civil engineering.
But you know about patterns.
Keep looking.
PAVEL:
It's done.
This is now a 4-megaton nuclear bomb.
BANE:
Pull the core out of the reactor.
PAVEL:
No, you cannot.
This is the only power source
capable of sustaining it.
If you move it,
the core will decay in a matter of months.
BANE:
Five, by my calculations.
And then it will go off!
BANE: And for the sake of your children,
Dr. Pavel...
...indeed I hope it does.
Hey. Hey!
That was you in front
of the stock exchange, wasn't it?
- When?
When cops were trying to pull onto Castle
Street and your truck was shutting them out.
- Oh, yeah. You're the cop.
- Detective now.
And, uh, as a detective, we're not
allowed to believe in coincidence.
What were you doing here?
What are you working on?
Commissioner, it's Blake.
I got two dead witnesses
and a lot of questions. Call me whenev...
Wait a minute. I'm looking at
four barrels of polyisobutylene.
That looks like motor oil right next to it.
Jesus, they're not making cement.
They're making explosives.
- Patch me in to Foley.
DISPATCH: Foley's overseeing the operation.
They're heading into a trap!
REPORTER: We're seeing thousands of police
heading into the sewers.
- Mr. Mayor? Literally thousands.
- It's a training exercise, that's all.
Now if you'll excuse me, I've got tickets
to watch our boys thrash Rapid City.
- Foley.
BLAKE: It's a trap! Pull everyone out!
Bane has been pouring concrete...
...laced with explosives!
- Where?
(SINGING) Oh, say, can you see
By the dawn's early light
What so proudly we hailed
At the twilight's...
BLAKE: There's a ring around the tunnels!
They'll blow it and trap the cops underground!
Pull them out. Pull them out now!
SINGER:
Through the perilous fight
O'er the ramparts we watched
Were so gallantly streaming
And the rockets' red glare
The bombs bursting in air
Gave proof through...
BANE:
That's a lovely, lovely voice.
...that our ﬂag was still there
Oh, say does that star-spangled banner
Yet wave
O'er the land of the free
And the home of the brave
(CHEERING)
(WHISTLE BLOWS)
BANE:
Let the games begin.
(RUMBLING)
(OFFICERS YELLING)
(CROWD SCREAMING)
COP 1:
Everybody okay?
COP 2: Let's move! Move, move!
COP 3: Go, go!
BANE:
Gotham...
...take control.
Take control of your city.
- Foley.
- Jesus, Blake.
Every cop in the city's in those tunnels.
Not every cop.
(MEDICAL DEVICE BEEPING)
Sir, are you okay? I'm a police officer.
I need your car right now.
(HORN HONKING)
(GUNSHOTS NEARBY)
Clear the corners, rookie.
Get my coat, son.
BANE:
This...
This is the instrument of your liberation.
ANALYST:
Satellite shows a radiation spike.
Whatever it is, it's nuclear.
BANE:
Identify yourself to the world.
Dr. Leonid Pavel, nuclear physicist.
Pavel was confirmed dead.
Plane crash on an agency pull
out of Uzbekistan, but...
It looks like it's him.
BANE:
And what...? What is this?
It's a fully primed neutron bomb...
...with a blast radius of six miles.
BANE: And who is capable of disarming
such a device?
Only me.
BANE:
Only you.
Thank you, good doctor!
(CROWD SCREAMS)
Now, this bomb is armed!
And this bomb is mobile!
And the identity of the triggerman
is a mystery.
For one of you holds the detonator!
Now, we come here
not as conquerors...
...but as liberators, to return control
of this city to the people.
And at the first sign of interference
from the outside world...
...or from those people
attempting to flee...
...this anonymous Gothamite...
...this unsung hero, will trigger the bomb.
For now, martial law is in effect.
Return to your homes,
hold your families close...
...and wait.
Tomorrow, you claim
what is rightfully yours.
GENERAL:
Pull back the fighters.
Start high-level reconnaissance flights.
Get the president on the line.
MERCENARY 1: Tanks and planes
cannot stop us from detonating our device.
Send an emissary to discuss terms of access
for supplies and communication.
CAPTAIN:
How many of you are there, son?
You don't have enough men to stop
12 million people from leaving this island.
No. No, we don't.
But you do.
(CHUCKLES)
Now, why the hell would I try
to help you keep your hostages?
If one person crosses this bridge...
...Gotham gets blown to hell.
The people of our greatest
city are resilient.
They have proven this before,
and they will prove it again.
We do not negotiate with terrorists...
...but we do recognize realities.
As this situation develops...
...one thing must be understood
above all others.
People of Gotham,
we have not abandoned you.
What does that mean?
It means we're on our own.
I have to get in front of a camera.
They will kill you the second
you show your face.
Bane says he's giving Gotham back to the people.
They need to know I could lead.
Bane's not gonna let that happen.
Then he'll show his true colors.
And you'll be dead.
BANE:
Behind you stands a symbol of oppression.
Blackgate Prison...
...where a thousand men have languished...
...under the name of this man:
Harvey Dent.
Who has been held up to you...
...as the shining example of justice!
We're just gonna keep moving you
till we can get you in front of the camera.
BANE: You have been supplied
with a false idol to stop you...
...tearing down this corrupt city!
Yes! Yes! Yes!
BANE: Let me tell you the
truth about Harvey Dent.
From the words of Gotham's
police commissioner...
...James Gordon:
"The Batman didn't murder Harvey Dent.
He saved my boy...
...then took the blame
for Harvey's appalling crimes...
...so that I could, to my shame...
...build a lie around this...
...fallen idol.
I praised the madman
who tried to murder my own child.
Well, I can no longer live with my lie.
It is time to trust the people of Gotham
with the truth...
...and it is time for me to resign. "
And do you accept this man's resignation?
(INMATES YELLING)
And do you accept the resignation
of all of these liars?
Of all the corrupt?
BLAKE: Those men locked up
for eight years in Blackgate...
...and denied parole under the Dent Act,
it was based on a lie.
Gotham needed a hero.
Well, it needs it now more than ever,
but you betrayed everything you stood for.
There's a point far out there
when the structures fail you...
...when the rules aren't
weapons any more...
...they're shackles,
letting the bad guy get ahead.
One day, you may face...
...such a moment of crisis.
And in that moment,
I hope you have a friend like I did...
...to plunge their hands into the filth,
so that you can keep yours clean!
Your hands look plenty filthy to me,
commissioner.
BANE:
We take Gotham from the corrupt!
The rich!
The oppressors of generations...
...who have kept you down
with myths of opportunity.
And we give it back to you...
...the people.
Gotham is yours!
None shall interfere. Do as you please.
But start by storming Blackgate
and freeing the oppressed!
MAN:
Open it!
BANE:
Step forward, those who would serve...
...for an army will be raised.
The powerful will be ripped
from their decadent nests...
...and cast out into the cold world
that we know and endure!
Courts will be convened.
Spoils will be enjoyed.
Blood will be shed!
The police will survive...
...as they learn to serve true justice.
This great city...
...it will endure.
Gotham will survive!
(GROANING)
(GRUNTING)
(BLIND PRISONER
SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
He says you must first fix your back.
WAYNE:
How does he know?
PRISONER:
He was the prison doctor.
He's a morphine addict
who incurred the displeasure...
...of powerful people,
including your masked friend.
How?
Many years ago, it was a time of plague.
Some of the other prisoners attacked Bane.
The doctor's fumbling attempts
to repair the damage...
...left him in perpetual agony.
The mask holds the pain at bay.
Bane was the child you spoke of?
He was born here?
The legend is that there was a mercenary
who worked for a local warlord.
He fell in love with
the warlord's daughter.
They were married in secret.
When the warlord found out...
...the mercenary was condemned to this pit.
But then he exiled him instead.
The mercenary understood that it was
the daughter who had secured his release.
But what he could not know
was the true price of his freedom.
She took his place in the pit.
And she was with child...
...the mercenary's child.
Innocence cannot flower underground.
It has to be stamped out.
One day, the doctor forgot
to lock the cell.
But the child had a friend...
...a protector who showed the others
that this innocence was their redemption.
It was to be prized.
The mother was not so lucky.
(SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
This is Bane's prison now.
He wouldn't want this story told.
(YELLING)
There's a vertebra protruding
from your back.
It has to be put back.
(YELLS)
Stay like this until you stand.
RA'S AL GHUL: Tsk, tsk, tsk, Did you
not think I would return, Bruce? Hmm?
(RA'S AL GHUL CHUCKLES)
I told you I was immortal.
I watched... I watched you die.
Oh, there are many forms of immortality.
Once, I had a wife...
...my great love.
- She was taken from me.
- You were the mercenary.
Bane is your child.
Your heir.
An heir to ensure
the League of Shadows fulfills its duty...
...to restore balance to civilization.
No.
You yourself fought the decadence
of Gotham for years...
...with all your strength...
...all your resources,
all your moral authority.
And the only victory you could
achieve was a lie.
Now you understand.
Gotham is beyond saving.
No.
- And must be allowed to die.
- No!
PRISONER:
Yeah, just lift your head.
Oh, that's good.
No, no!
JEN: What's that?
SELINA: This was someone's home.
JEN:
And now it's everyone's home.
There's a storm coming, remember?
This is what you wanted.
(CHATTERING)
It's for the bus,
in case there's a chance to evacuate.
Any news? Is the commissioner...?
The less you know, Father.
How are the boys doing?
REILLY: Well, we've had more power on,
so they've got some TV.
It's good to see you.
Blake, you be careful out there.
They're hunting down cops like dogs.
Why build yourself?
WAYNE: I'm not meant to die in here.
- Here, there. What's the difference?
(PRISONERS CHANTING)
(YELLS)
I told you it could not be done.
You told me a child did it.
(CHUCKLES)
But no ordinary child.
A child born in hell.
Forged from suffering.
Hardened by pain.
Not a man from privilege.
ANALYST:
We got boots on the ground, sir.
Just waiting on intel.
You have ID?
Of course not.
- Well, how can we trust you?
GORDON: We don't have any choice.
Commissioner Gordon.
Captain Jones, Special Forces.
Captain. Glad to have you here.
It's our job, sir.
Now, uh, how many of you are there?
Well, there's dozens.
I'd rather not say exactly.
But the men trapped underground
number almost 3000.
JONES: Condition?
GORDON: Getting food and water.
JONES: Can we break them out?
BLAKE: Yes, sir.
Take out the mercenaries
south of Ackerman Park.
Blow the rubble, make a hole
big enough for 10 at a time.
I'm in contact with my partner
who's down there. They're just waiting.
- Men who haven't seen daylight in months?
- Officers who haven't seen daylight in months.
What about the bomb? Satellite
can't pick up radiation hot spots.
GORDON: They keep it on a truck.
It must have a lead-lined roof.
- They move it constantly.
JONES: Good. So you know the truck?
GORDON: Well, it's one of three.
We've been tracking it.
Decoy.
- You don't really think he's coming back?
- Doesn't matter what I think.
Actually, it does. You should put your
faith in something a little more real.
GORDON: The routes don't vary much.
JONES: Okay. What about the triggerman?
No leads. It's a bluff. Bane wouldn't give
control of that bomb to someone else.
We can't take that chance. Until we have
the triggerman, we just track the device.
And meanwhile, Gotham lives under
a warlord, like some failed state?
Dial it back, officer.
This situation is unprecedented.
- We can't do anything to risk millions of lives.
- You gonna tell him what's really going on?
Captain, the situation is more
complicated than you think.
There's someone you need to meet.
Came upstairs looking for a vantage point.
Found the people who run the corporation.
What corporation?
Wayne Enterprises. You good?
Mr. Fox, would you like to brief
the captain?
Miss Tate's fully aware of the situation.
And as CEO of Wayne Enterprises,
I have to take responsibility for it.
- Why?
- We built it.
You built the bomb?
It was built as a fusion reactor.
First of its kind.
Bane turned the core into a bomb
and removed it from the reactor.
- Here's the important part.
- As the device's fuel cells deteriorate...
...it becomes increasingly unstable...
...to the point of detonation.
This bomb is a time bomb.
And it will go off in 23 days,
regardless of Bane's revolution...
...or what we, or the outside world,
choose to do.
So your plan might not be
as practical as you thought.
- Could you disarm it?
- I could reconnect it to the reactor. Stabilize it.
- Let's move from this location and call it in.
- Right. Let's go.
No, no, we'll take it from here.
You stay and look after these folks.
(GUNFIRE)
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
Someone sold us out.
Go, go, go!
I'll die before I talk.
BANE:
I'm on your schedule, captain.
(GRUNTS)
MERCENARY:
There were people living upstairs.
BANE:
Round them up forjudgment...
...and hang them where the world can see.
REPORTER: Police have cordoned off the entire
Central Heights and East Park Side areas...
...as well as Merchant and South Shoreline
Boulevards in an attempt...
(BLIND PRISONER SPEAKS
IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
He says the leap to freedom
is not about strength.
My body makes the jump.
(IN ENGLISH)
Survival is the spirit. The soul.
My soul is as ready to escape as my body.
Fear is why you fail.
No, I'm not afraid.
I'm angry.
(PRISONERS CHANTING)
(GRUNTS)
THOMAS:
Bruce.
Why do we fall?
(GASPS)
BLIND PRISONER:
You do not fear death.
You think this makes you strong.
It makes you weak.
Why?
How can you move faster than possible...
...fight longer than possible...
...without the most powerful impulse
of the spirit?
The fear of death.
I do fear death.
I fear dying in here...
...while my city burns.
There's no one there to save it.
Then make the climb.
(CHUCKLES)
How?
As the child did...
...without the rope.
Then fear will find you again.
Ah, supplies for your journey?
Oh, that's wonderful. That's...
(PRISONERS CHANTING)
What does that mean?
Rise.
No.
(SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE)
(CHEERING)
No, there's been a mistake!
Take me to Bane!
I want to see Bane!
CRANE:
Order!
This is a mistake! Where is Bane?
CRANE:
There's been no mistake, Mr. Stryver.
You are Philip Stryver...
...executive vice president
of Daggett Industries...
...who for years has been living off
the blood and sweat...
...of people less powerful than him.
Call Bane. I am one of you.
CRANE: Bane has no authority here.
This is merely a sentencing hearing.
Now, the choice is yours.
Exile or death!
(ALL SHOUTING AND CHEERING)
CRANE:
Order!
Exi... Exile.
Sold.
To the man in the cold sweat.
You follow the thick ice.
You try to swim, you're dead in minutes.
Has anyone made it?
GORDON: Where are they?
It's not like we have a lot of time.
VETERAN COP:
How long?
The bomb goes off tomorrow.
- We have about 18 hours to do something.
- To do what?
GORDON: To mark the truck. Get a GPS on it so we
can start to figure out how to bring it down.
That's it?
Foley.
- Where's Foley, damn it?
- You shouldn't be out on the streets.
- Jim, he's not here.
- You let your wife come to the door?
- When the city's under occupation?
- Wait in the kitchen, honey.
What did you do,
bury your uniform in the backyard?
You saw what they did
to those Special Forces.
Have you forgotten all the years
we were out on patrol?
When every gangbanger wanted to plant one
as soon as our backs were turned?
That was different. These guys run the city.
The government's done a deal with them.
Bane's got their balls in a vice.
That's not a deal.
You move on Bane,
the triggerman is gonna hit the button.
You think he's given control of that bomb
to one of the people?
You think this is part of some revolution?
There's one man with his finger
on the button. That's Bane.
Look, we've all got to keep our heads
down till they can fix this.
- If you still had a family here...
- This only gets fixed from inside...
...the city!
Look, Peter.
I'm not asking you to walk down Grand in your
dress blues, but something has to be done.
- Sorry, Jim. I gotta...
- Keep your head down?
What goods that gonna do
when that thing blows?
You don't know that's gonna happen.
(DOOR LOCKS)
MIRANDA: I hear you're looking for men,
commissioner.
How about me instead?
Miss Tate, I, uh, can't ask you to do that.
Please.
GANGBANGER:
You little punk! What'd you take?
KID:
Nothing! I didn't take anything!
You steal from us, you little bastard?
Now, you boys know you can't come into
my neighborhood without asking politely.
Never steal anything from someone
you can't outrun, kid.
WAYNE:
You're pretty generous for a thief.
- I thought they killed you.
- Not yet.
- If you're expecting an apology, I...
- It wouldn't suit you.
I need your help.
And why would I help you?
For this. Clean slate.
You'd trust me with that?
After what I did to you?
I'll admit, I was a little let down.
But I still think there's more to you.
In fact, I think that for you...
...this isn't just a tool.
It's an escape route.
You want to disappear. Start fresh.
- I can't even get off this island.
- I can give you a way off...
...once you get me to Lucius Fox.
Find out where they're holding him
and take me in.
Why do you need Fox?
- To save the city.
- Who says it needs saving?
Maybe I like it this way.
Maybe you do...
...but tomorrow that bomb's going off.
Got your powerful friend on the case?
I'm trying...
...but I need Fox.
As it approaches...
...flip the switch.
The needle hits 200, you give me the
signal, I'll mark the truck. Okay?
Heads up, heads up.
- I got it.
- Mercenaries on your 6.
MERCENARY: Stand still! Keep your hands
where we can see them!
Commissioner Gordon,
you are under arrest.
GORDON:
On whose authority?
The people of Gotham.
No lawyer? No witnesses?
What sort of due process is this?
CRANE: Your guilt has been determined,
this is merely a sentencing hearing.
Now, what will it be?
Death or exile?
Crane, if you think we're going out
onto that ice willingly...
...you have another thing coming.
Death, then.
- Looks that way.
CRANE: Very well.
Death...
...by exile.
(ALL SHOUTING)
BANE:
Bring her to me.
ROSS: Hey, we're going now.
Blake says they're ready! Get your gear on!
Hey, you hear me?
We're going now. Let's do it.
MERCENARY 1: Find this one a spot,
got a big day tomorrow.
MERCENARY 2: We all do.
It's not every day you bag Bruce Wayne.
- Bruce.
WAYNE: You okay?
Picked a hell of a time to go on vacation,
Mr. Wayne.
How long until that core ignites?
- That bomb goes off in 12 hours.
- Unless we can reconnect it to the reactor.
- Can you get Miranda out of here?
- Not tonight. I'm sorry.
- Do what's necessary.
WAYNE: Tonight I need you.
FOX: What for?
- To get me back in the game.
Sorry to spoil things, boys,
but Bane wants these guys to himself.
- I won't forget about you, Miranda.
- I know.
I like your girlfriend, Mr. Wayne.
He should be so lucky.
Any move I make on Bane or the bomb...
...the triggerman sets it off.
FOX: Well, they won't use radio or cell.
Too much interference.
Infrared doesn't have the range.
It'll have to be a microburst. Longwave.
- Could you block it?
- Yes.
But I'll need the EMP cannon
guidance mount from the Bat.
Remember where you parked?
She ﬂy okay?
Yeah, even without the autopilot.
- Thanks.
- Autopilot? That's what you're there for.
ROSS: Okay. It's clear. Come on, quick.
One at a time.
(GUNSHOT)
COP 1:
Wait, wait!
COP 2:
Ross!
COP 3:
Ross?
- Lock it up.
COP 3: No, keep down.
COP 4:
Get down!
Who are you?
BATMAN:
Light it up.
BOY: Dad, check it out.
MRS. FOLEY: Honey, come take a look.
BANE:
Impossible.
Keep her close.
He'll come for her.
BATMAN:
Where's Miranda Tate?
Bane took her.
He's holed up at city hall,
surrounded by his army.
This blocks the remote detonator signal
to the bomb.
Get it onto it before sunrise.
They might hit the button when it starts.
When what starts?
War.
(GUN COCKS)
You missed a spot.
- If you're working alone, wear a mask.
- I'm not afraid to be seen standing up to them.
The mask is not for you.
It's to protect the people you care about.
Count to five, then throw.
(DEVICE BEEPING)
No offense, but you got
something bigger in that belt?
- What now?
- All-out assault on Bane.
But you need to get people
across the bridge.
- Why?
- In case we fail.
Lead an exodus.
Save as many lives as you can.
You don't need me here?
You've given me an army.
Now go.
Hey, thanks.
Don't thank me yet.
Well, I might not get a chance later.
You shouldn't have.
BATMAN: The midtown tunnel's
blocked by debris...
...but the cannons have enough firepower
to make a path for people.
Wait until the fighting begins.
You're gonna wage a war
to save your stuck-up girlfriend?
To start it, throttle...
(ENGINE REVS)
- I got it.
- We have 45 minutes to save this city.
No, I've got 45 minutes to get clear
of the blast radius.
- You don't stand a chance against these guys.
- With your help, I might.
I'll open that tunnel, then I'm gone.
There's more to you than that.
Sorry to keep letting you down.
Come with me.
Save yourself.
You don't owe these people any more.
You've given them everything.
Not everything.
Not yet.
MERCENARY (OVER BULLHORN):
Disperse!
Disperse or be fired upon!
There's only one police in this town.
(MERCENARIES CLAMORING)
BANE:
Open fire.
(cops CHEER)
- Here it comes!
- Get ready!
BANE:
So you came back to die with your city.
No. I came back to stop you.
Now!
That's impossible.
Cut over to Fifth!
Here you go. Get on the bus. Go ahead.
You, come with me. You too.
Hey, you, you, and you,
come here, come here.
Everyone else get on the bus, okay?
You guys, you go knock on doors
and spread the word, okay?
The bomb is gonna go off. Get out by
the South Street tunnel or over the bridge.
You do two blocks and you get back
to the bus, all right?
Go, go, go!
Is he back?
Keep your eyes open. Go, go.
(MASK HISSES & BANE GROANS)
(BANE YELLING)
BATMAN:
Cover the doors!
Where's your trigger?!
Where is it?!
You'd never give it
to an ordinary citizen!
Where is it? Where's your trigger?
(MASK HISSING)
Where is it?! Where is it?!
Tell me where the trigger is.
Then you have my permission to die.
BANE:
I broke you.
How have you come back?
You think you're the only one who could
learn the strength to escape?
Where's the trigger?
BANE:
But I never escaped.
But the child.
The child of Ra's Al Ghul made the climb.
MIRANDA:
But he's not the child of Ra's Al Ghul.
(BATMAN GRUNTS)
I am.
And though I'm not ordinary...
...I am a citizen.
BATMAN:
Miranda?
Why?
Talia.
My mother named me Talia,
before she was killed...
...the way I would have been killed,
if not for my protector...
...Bane.
Goodbye.
TALIA:
I climbed out of the pit.
I found my father...
...and brought him back
to exact terrible vengeance.
But by that time...
...the prisoners and doctor had done
their work to my friend.
My protector.
The League took us in.
Trained us.
But my father could not accept Bane.
He saw only a monster.
His very existence was a reminder
of the hell he'd left his wife to die in.
He excommunicated Bane
from the League of Shadows.
His only crime was that he loved me.
I could not forgive my father.
Until you murdered him.
(BEEPING)
He was trying to kill millions
of innocent people.
Innocent is a strong word
to throw around Gotham, Bruce.
I honor my father by finishing his work.
Vengeance against the man who killed him
is simply a reward for my patience.
You see...
...it's the slow knife...
...the knife that takes its time.
The knife...
...that waits years without forgetting...
...then slips quietly between the bones.
That's the knife...
...that cuts deepest.
Please.
(DETONATOR CLICKS)
Maybe your knife...
...was too slow.
MERCENARY:
The truck is under attack.
Gordon.
You gave him a way to block my signal.
No matter.
(GRUNTS)
He's bought Gotham 11 minutes.
(BEEPING)
Come on!
This Way!
COP:
Stay there! What are you doing?
Blake, MCU!
I'm getting these boys to safety!
You'll get us all killed!
If anyone crosses this bridge,
they'll blow the city!
It's gonna blow anyway!
We need to open this bridge, now!
Detective, if you take one step forward
we will shoot you!
If you take two steps forward,
we will blow the bridge!
Okay, go back by the bus and wait for me,
all right? Go back and wait.
TALIA: Prepare a convoy. We must secure
the bomb until it detonates.
Don't kill him,
I want him to feel the heat.
Feel the fire of 12
million souls you failed.
Goodbye, my friend.
BANE:
Goodbye.
Keep moving forward!
Flank them at the stairs!
Shoot them.
Shoot them all.
(GUNFIRE)
BANE:
We both know that I have to kill you now.
You'll just have to imagine the fire.
(PANTING)
About the whole no-guns thing...
...I'm not sure I feel as strongly
about it as you do.
Pull up.
Stay level.
We have to force that convoy east
to the entrance to the reactor.
I need you on the ground,
I'll be in the air. Go.
The situation has changed.
Your orders are out of date.
I'm a cop, like you,
and I'm walking out there.
Please do not shoot me!
Shoot at his feet.
Nothing like a little air superiority.
Detective! Please stop!
Please, detective! Stop!
Stop walking!
Blow it! Do it!
You have to get that bomb here.
You've got 10 minutes.
They're pushing us
to the entrance of the reactor.
They're gonna try to reconnect the core.
You idiots!
You sons of bitches!
You're killing us!
Yeah, follow your orders!
All right, boys. Get in a circle.
Bow your heads.
It's on my side.
(PANEL BEEPING)
(BEEPING)
BLAKE: Hey, Father! Let's get everyone back
on the bus, okay? Go, go, go!
- Back on the bus!
- There's nowhere to go.
On the bus!
FOX:
You've got to turn the truck east!
Stay straight!
(COMPUTER BEEPS)
Give me a hand!
We can get a cable on it!
Fox showed me how to override
the reactor.
Oh, dear.
(ALARM WAILING)
Including the emergency flood.
TALIA:
There's no way...
...this bomb...
...will be stopped.
What are you doing?
Protection from the blast.
We're gonna be all right!
It's an atom bomb!
Think they need to hear that?
Let them die without hope? Come on!
Prepare yourselves.
My father's work...
...is done.
GORDON: What are you doing?
BATMAN: I can get it out over the bay!
CATWOMAN: Set it to fly out
over the water, then eject?
BATMAN:
No autopilot.
You could've gone anywhere, been anything.
But you came back here.
So did you.
I guess we're both suckers.
- I never cared who you were.
- And you were right.
Shouldn't the people know
the hero who saved them?
A hero can be anyone.
Even a man doing something
as simple and reassuring...
...as putting a coat around a young boy's
shoulders to let him know...
...the world hadn't ended.
Bruce Wayne?
Come on! There you go!
Okay, you too. Come on, Father.
Hey, heads down! This is it!
- No.
- No, that's Batman!
(BEEPING)
That's detonation!
It's out over the bay! Clear of the city!
(CHEERING)
GORDON:
"I see a beautiful city...
...and a brilliant people...
...rising from this abyss.
I see the lives for which
I lay down my life...
...peaceful...
...useful, prosperous and happy.
I see that I hold a sanctuary
in their hearts...
...and in the hearts
of their descendants...
...generations hence.
It is a far, far better thing that I do...
...than I have ever done.
It is a far, far better
rest that I go to...
...than I have ever known. "
(ALFRED SOBBING)
ALFRED:
I'm so sorry.
I failed you.
You trusted me...
...and I failed you.
Can I change your mind...
...about quitting the force?
You know what you said about
structures becoming shackles?
You were right, and I can't take it.
The injustice.
I mean, no one's ever gonna know
who saved an entire city.
They know.
It was the Batman.
LAWYER: Mr. Wayne's will was not amended
to reflect his more modest estate.
Nonetheless, there are considerable
assets to dispose of.
The contents of the house are to be sold
to settle the estate's accounts...
...and the remainder is left in its
entirety to Alfred J. Pennyworth.
The house and grounds are left to
the city of Gotham on condition that...
...they never be demolished,
altered or otherwise interfered with...
...and that they shall be used for
one purpose, and one purpose only:
The housing and care of the city's
at-risk and orphaned children.
My clerk can help with the smaller
correspondences and instructions.
BLAKE:
Blake, John.
- Nothing here.
- Uh, try my legal name.
You should use your full name.
I like that name.
- Robin.
- Thanks.
SCIENTIST 1: Why worry about
the stabilization software?
This entire autopilot system's
completely obsolete.
Please, I just need to know
what I could've done to fix it.
But, Mr. Fox, it's already been fixed.
Software patch. Six months ago.
Check the ID on the patch.
SCIENTIST 2:
Bruce Wayne.
- Any news on the missing item?
- Not yet.
They better leave no stone unturned.
We can't leave a string of pearls
on the manifest as lost.
(English - US - SDH)